Bottom line decision. בוקר טוב, Boker tov, let's see, bottom line
decision.
This is about what? It's the choices yesterday, you know, about multiple
punishments and between death... No, I mean it's a range of opinions.
Yeah, yeah. All right, so today's דף daf is ל"ו, Lamed Vav,
36, and we pick up in the middle of... we actually are
a good bit ahead. We pick up in the...
where it is, two dots towards the bottom third, אילונית אין לה
קנס. ilanit ein lah knas. So we are... we have for the
time finished with the discussion of קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, kim lei
b'deraba minei, which was an amazing seven דפים dafim סוגיא, sugya, as
I was just sort of discussing here before we got started. You
know, the גמרא, Gemara, there's... just to remind you of the different
opinions, right? The way the גמרא Gemara sort of phrased it at
the end, which is that if it was a sin that you're
חייב מיתה chayav misa for מיתה בית דין, misa Beis Din, then
the גמרא Gemara at least phrased it... תוספות Tosfos asks if this
is necessarily true, but that everybody would agree that that would override
a monetary payment, even if it was a case of שוגג shogeg
or the like. If it was a case of כרת, kares, then
that was the position of רבי נחוניא בן הקנה, Rabbi Nechunya ben
HaKanah, and that was debated. If it was a case of מלקות,
malkus, there was a more wide-range debate where you had רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that said you could get both punishments, you had עולא
Ulla that said you would pay rather than get מלקות, malkus, or
תוספות Tosfos said that might have only been in the case of
our case about the קנס knas of אונס ומפתה. ones umefate, And
then you had the standard position, which is you would get מלקות
malkus and not pay, and within there, there was a debate of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan וריש לקיש, v'Resh Lakish, whereas רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said only if that מלקות malkus was actually administered, and ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish says even if it was a שוגג shogeg and
if there wasn't התראה hatara and if מלקות malkus wasn't administered. So
we have the whole nice wide range of possibilities. Okay, the גמרא
Gemara now, anyway, is turning back to the issue of the women
that do or don't have a קנס, knas, not from the קים
ליה kimlei perspective but from the perspective of their personal status. So
we have our משנה mishna says whether it's עריות, arayos, as long
as it's not in the category of חייב מיתה, chayav misa, but
a case of like sister or whatever, would even get... the fact
that the marriage is not binding would not prevent it, although... and
then we have a ברייתא beraisa that actually excluded the עריות, arayos,
reflecting the position of either רבי שמעון התימני Rabbi Shimon Hatimani or
רבי שמעון בן מנסיא, Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya, who would say that
the קנס knas would only be paid if it was a case
with a woman who marriage could be binding, or even more restrictive,
if marriage was actually permitted. And now we're going back... so that's
one issue about the personal status in terms of עריות, arayos, and
then we're getting to the issue about whether it only applies to
a נערה na'arah or even to a קטנה. ketana. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says only a נערה, na'arah, the חכמים chachamim say even a
קטנה, ketana, and the גמרא Gemara had an application of that in
terms of the case of an אילונית, ilanit, of a woman who
never gets physical maturity, so she goes from being considered a קטנה
ketana at the age of twenty to being considered a בוגרת, bogeret,
she never is in the stage of נערה, na'arah, the puberty stage.
And therefore, this ברייתא beraisa that we were dealing with, not our
משנה mishna but the ברייתא beraisa we're dealing with starting yesterday, said
that she would not get a קנס knas because this ברייתא beraisa
is assuming that only a נערה na'arah gets a קנס. knas. The
only... the other issue in the ברייתא beraisa that we're going to
turn to now is the question not about נערה, na'arah, not about
עריות, arayos, but the question about whether the woman is considered to
be a בתולה besula or not. And to some degree, we dealt
with it yesterday also in the case of ממאנת, mema'enet, a girl
who's not halachically married but who is, I mean, is rabbinically married
but not דאורייתא de'oraisa married and is living with another man, and
that she cannot be assumed to be a בתולה, besula, and now
we're going to... now we're going to deal with other cases about
the aspect of the בתולה besula part of the definition. Yes.
Have we been using תשלומין tashlumin and קנס knas interchangeably?
So the גמרא Gemara basically has assumed that all monetary payments are
the same in terms of the קים ליה kimlei discussion, although if
you'll remember, within רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it dealt with the possibility
that קנס knas might be a more of an exception, that maybe
you don't pay normal compensation in the place of a חייב מיתה
chayav misa but you might pay a קנס knas in the case
of a חייב מיתה. chayav misa. So there are potential differences in
terms of the קים ליה kimlei discussion. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues with the אילונית ilanit issue and the other types of
women that not just from נערה na'arah perspective but from a question
of בתולה besula perspective would not get the קנס, knas, and it's
about twenty lines from the bottom, and the line starts with the
word אילונית. ilanit. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: אילונית
אין לה קנס, ilanit ein lah knas, an אילונית ilanit doesn't have
a קנס, knas, ולא פיתוי, v'lo pituach, or if a case of
seduction, she doesn't get the קנס knas for that. Okay, ורמינהו, u-remihu,
that was the ברייתא beraisa we had yesterday, and again, presumably from
the perspective that she's never a נערה. na'arah. Now I'll ask you
on this: it says החרשת והשוטה והאילונית, hachereshet v'hashota v'hailanis, a woman
who is a חרשת, chereshet, a deaf-mute, so she's not considered to
be a בר דעת, bar da'at, and we'll see why that's relevant...
of relevance in a minute, or שוטה, shota, a woman that is...
you know, has a mental illness that does not allow them to
act normally, you know, in interacting with the larger world, interpret and
act normally in the larger world, והאילונית, v'hailanis, or again, this woman.
who never has never achieved physical maturity. יש לה קנס, yesh lah
knas, they have a קנס. knas. Okay, so that's so that's so
the so the so that's
so the חרש ושוטה cheresh ve'shoteh is new information. אילונית יש לה
קנס ilonit yesh lah knas contradicts the ברייתא baraita that says אין
לה קנס. ein lah knas. We know that the issue with the
אילונית ilonit is that she's never a נערה. na'ara. Okay, so that's
one area of contradiction. And then the ברייתא baraita goes on and
introduces a new aspect: ויש להם טענת בתולים. ve'yeshem ta'anas betulim. Now,
טענת בתולים, ta'anas betulim, you'll remember going back to the first פרק,
perek, is the issue that the husband wakes up... comes to bed
in the morning after the wedding and says 'I was expecting her
to be a בתולה, betula, she's not a בתולה, betula, and therefore
she shouldn't have... her כתובה kesuva should go down from 200 to
100 or she shouldn't get any כתובה kesuva because it wasn't what
I expected.' So יש לה טענת בתולים yesh lah ta'anas betulim is
not a good thing—I mean, not a good thing for her. It
means that the husband has a right to claim that he was...
he was cheated; he was expecting her to be a בתולה betula
and she wasn't.
But does she have any מיגו miggo because she can't...?
All right, so those are all the discussions, so we'll get to
that. Those are all discussions of the first פרק perek and it
might be different here because of the women... because of the women
we're talking about. Very good. So we'll get to that. What about
פיתוי? pitoy? Okay, let's not... let's ignore פיתוי pitoy for now. And
but the relevant point of ויש להם טענת בתולים ve'yeshem ta'anas betulim
is that can it be assumed that they are בתולה? betula? Okay,
which is consistent with יש להם קנס. yesh lahem knas. So all
these women, even though they're חרש, cheresh, שוטה, shoteh, and אילונית ilonit
that maybe you might think... actually you might reasonably think that these
are women that maybe... certainly the חרש cheresh and the שוטה, shoteh,
the חרשת chereshet and the שוטה, shota,
that maybe people would take advantage of them and therefore maybe you
might have to be concerned that they're not a בתולה. betula. So
definitely with those two there's a definite חידוש chiddush that they have
a קנס knas and they have טענת בתולים, ta'anas betulim, which both
of them reflect the fact that we assume that they are בתולה.
betula. Okay, but the seeming contradiction that we're first introducing is the
אילונית ilonit has a קנס knas in our ברייתא baraita and the
ברייתא baraita says it doesn't. So the גמרא Gemara said, 'והא מאי
רמיא? ve'hai mai rumiya? What type of contradiction is that? הא רבי
מאיר הא רבנן.' ha Rabi Meir ha Rabanan. We just got through
saying that the whole issue with the אילונית ilonit is that she's
never a נערה. na'ara. She goes from being a קטנה ketana to
a בוגרת. bogeret. So fine, so the ברייתא baraita that says she
doesn't have a קנס knas is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says
that only a נערה na'ara has a קנס knas and the ברייתא
baraita you just quoted that says she does get a קנס knas
is the רבנן Rabanan that says even a קטנה ketana gets a
קנס. knas. So big deal, we all know what the debate about
אילונית ilonit could be. It's not a problem that one ברייתא baraita
says one way, one says the other. So the גמרא Gemara said,
'וקארי לה מאי קארי לה? ve'ka'arei lei mai ka'arei lei? So what
actually even occurred to you that made you think that you could
ask this as a problem? I mean, clearly this is a debate
of תנאים Tanna'im about אילונית ilonit reflecting the debate about... about whether
a קטנה ketana has a קנס. knas. So the גמרא Gemara says,
'משום דאית ליה דמר מאחריתי עלוהי.' mishum de'is lei de'mir me'achrisi aloyei.
Right, it's right, he knew that this ברייתא baraita could be answered
up, but he had another ברייתא, baraita, he wanted to bring this
ברייתא baraita into the conversation as it were, because he had another
ברייתא baraita that was even more of a problem and he wanted
to like put all these issues on the table. What's the other
ברייתא baraita he wanted to bring onto... he wanted to bring into
the conversation? The following: החרשת והשוטה והבוגרת
ומוכת עץ אין להם טענת בתולים.
ha'chereshet ve'hashota ve'habogeret ve'mukat eitz ein
lahem ta'anas betulim. So a חרשת chereshet and a שוטה shota cannot
be assumed to be a בתולה. betula. And therefore if the husband
gets... comes to bed the next morning and says 'Oh she wasn't
a בתולה,' betula, we say tough luck, you should have expected that,
and you have no... and you have no טענה. ta'ana. Okay, so
now, בוגרת bogeret and מוכת עץ mukat eitz are more obvious. מוכת
עץ mukat eitz is a woman who actually we know has some
type of physical injury and therefore is not a בתולה betula at
least from the sense of not having the hymen intact.
בוגרת, bogeret, you might remember we discussed in the first פרק, perek,
once she reaches the age of... she passes puberty, right? So is
it considered that that will therefore... the hymen will be thinned out
or whatever, and therefore, you know, either she won't have the hymen
or that we can't trust his claim that... that it wasn't there
or there won't be... or there won't be necessarily blood to prove
it. But whatever it is, once she's of that age, there's no
longer claim... his claim that she was not a בתולה betula is
no longer accepted. So מוכת עץ mukat eitz and בוגרת bogeret we'll
get back to; those are issues we dealt with in the first
פרק. perek. But חרשת chereshet and שוטה shota here, it says you
can't assume they're a virgin. Again, the assumption I would have made
would be because you assume that they were... people would take advantage
of them. So here's a contradiction: one ברייתא baraita says that you
can assume they're a virgin, they get a קנס knas and if
they're not a virgin the husband has a טענת בתולים ta'anas betulim
the next morning; and this ברייתא baraita says that there isn't a
טענת בתולים, ta'anas betulim, which presumably means that you can't assume they're
a virgin. So we've got... he really just quoted the ברייתא baraita
of אילונית, ilonit, he knew there was an answer to אילונית, ilonit,
he wanted to have a discussion about חרשת chereshet and שוטה shota
and to show that there's a contradiction in the ברייתות baraitot between
whether חרשת chereshet and שוטה shota can be assumed to be a
virgin or not. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
I'm sorry, but now we have the end of this ברייתא, baraita,
and הסומא והאילונית יש להם טענת בתולים. ha'suma ve'ha'ilonit yesh lahem ta'anas
betulim. A blind woman and an אילונית, ilonit, those are assumed to
be virgins. So אילונית ilonit obviously, the whole issue there was a
קנס knas issue about whether she was because she wasn't a נערה,
na'ara, but of course we can assume that she'll be a virgin.
And a blind woman also, we should assume that she... סומכוס אומר
משום רבי מאיר סומא אין לה טענת בתולים.
Sumchos Omer Mishum Rebbe
Meir Suma Ein Lah Ta'anat Betulim. But סומכוס Sumchos says in the
name of רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, no, that even a blind woman
cannot be assumed to be a virgin and she doesn't have a
טענת בתולים Ta'anat Betulim the next morning if she isn't. So that's
interesting what the issue is about the blind woman. But let's we're
bracketing the blind woman, we're bracketing the איילונית Ayalonit and the בוגרת.
Bogeret. Right now what we've put on the table is a seeming
contradiction in ברייתות Baraitas whether we assume that a חרשת Chereshet and
a שוטה Shotah are virgins or not. So let's see what the
גמרא's Gemara's answer is. אמר רב ששת לא קשיא, Amar Rav Sheshet
Lo Kashya, it's not difficult. הא רבן גמליאל והא רבי יהושע. Ha
Rabban Gamliel Ve-Ha Rebbe Yehoshua. So now it is exactly introducing the
point that Michael made which is that it's not the difference about
if there was a מחלוקת Machlokes about whether they had a קנס
Knas or not, then you would say that the question is whether
they're assumed to be virgins or not. But the only contradiction in
the ברייתות Baraitas was not whether they have a קנס, Knas, the
contradiction in the ברייתות Baraitas was whether there's טענת בתולים, Ta'anat Betulim,
whether the husband can make a claim she wasn't a בתולה Betula
and therefore be entitled to reduce her כתובה. Ketubah. So to say
that the husband can't make that claim, there could be more than
one reason. It doesn't just have to be for the reason like
oh well you should assume that a חרשת Chereshet and a שוטה
Shotah are not a virgin. No, maybe there's another reason he can't
make that claim, why not? So or he won't win with the
claim, he can make whatever claim he wants, but he won't win
with the claim. Why not? So you might remember the debate of
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua when a woman
comes and she responds, the husband says you weren't a בתולה Betula
and she has certain responses. Now she could always say yes I
was, you're lying, but she could also say you're right I wasn't
a בתולה Betula because I was raped after we got married, or
I wasn't a בתולה Betula because I'm a מוכת עץ, Mukat Etz,
right? So you always can have some different some type of various
claims you might remember from the earlier גמרא Gemara where based on
her response and based on different halakhic positions, it would explain why
there was no blood or why פתח פתוח Petach Patuach or whatever,
and at the same time it would not reduce her כתובה Ketubah
because there's a different explanation for the circumstances. So what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is when it says אין להם טענת בתולים, Ein
Lahem Ta'anat Betulim, it does not mean we assume they're not virgins.
We assume that a חרשת Chereshet and a שוטה Shotah is a
virgin and therefore everybody would agree that she gets a קנס. Knas.
But what it means is if the husband comes the next morning
and says I assumed you were a virgin and you weren't and
therefore I should be able to reduce the כתובה Ketubah or say
you're not going to win your claim. Why you're not going to
win your claim? So רש"י Rashi says because we could always claim
for her. Well, maybe she went like these are people that are
not בני דעת Bnei Da'at so they cannot submit represent themselves in
court, so we will represent them and we'll make the most advantageous
claim for them. So the claim might be yes she was a
virgin when she the קידושין, Kiddushin, but maybe she was raped afterwards,
okay? And we'll make that claim for her, so the husband's claim
won't win because we'll always defend her position. תוספות Tosafot says it's
not the defense that she was raped afterwards, it's the defense that
she became a מוכת עץ. Mukat Etz. But whatever it is, one
of the earlier defenses that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says wins is
a defense we'll make for her. So when it says that she
doesn't have a טענת בתולים, Ta'anat Betulim, it means that we will
represent her with the position of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that there
is a defense that she can that she can lodge that actually
will make her win the case. According to רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua
though, לא מפי אנו חיים, Lo Mipi Anu Chayim, you remember that
phrase of רבי יהושע, Rebbe Yehoshua, anything she says she won't win.
So when it says יש להם טענת בתולים, Yesh Lahem Ta'anat Betulim,
that's according to רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua that says there's no defense
that she can win. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says הא רבן
גמליאל והא רבי יהושע. Ha Rabban Gamliel Ve-Ha Rebbe Yehoshua. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute. אימור דשמעת ליה לרבן גמליאל, Eimur Deshamat
Lei Le-Rabban Gamliel, when did רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel say that if
she says certain things then the husband doesn't win? היכא דקא טענה
היא Heicha De-Ka Ta'ana Hee when she actually makes a particular claim
about explaining why she wasn't a virgin on the wedding night. But
היכא דלא קא טענה היא Heicha De-Lo Ka Ta'ana Hee if she's
not making that claim, מי שמעת ליה Mi Shamat Lei would he
ever say that she wins?
גמרא Gemara says אין, In, yes. כיון דאמר רבן גמליאל מהימנא, Keivan
De-Amar Rabban Gamliel Mehemana, since רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said she would
be believed with certain claims, שכגון זה פתח פיך לאלם הוא, She-Kegon
Zeh Ptach Picha L'Ilem Hu, just as a case of open up
your mouth for the mute, meaning so yes בית דין Beis Din
sometimes we'll defend and lodge these sort of make the arguments, the
טענות Ta'anot for the people that are not able to defend themselves.
Even though of course the irony is that sometimes the reason the
woman is believed is we'll say well she would never be so
brazen to lie about this in the presence of her husband, other
types of things that would not necessarily be true if somebody else
was waging the defense for her, or just the very fact that
it's a ברי, Bari, that when the woman says that she's making
a definite claim whereas when בית דין Beis Din is saying it
on her behalf they're making a doubtful claim. Nevertheless, sometimes if the
other person is not considered like a בר דעת Bar Da'at or
maybe is a minor or other types of cases, בית דין Beis
Din might actually present position themselves as that person and lodge the
best defense even on their behalf. Okay, so basically we've got a
contradiction in ברייתות Baraitas whether חרשת Chereshet and שוטה Shotah have a
טענת בתולים. Ta'anat Betulim. You could have said it was a debate
about whether we assume them to be virgins and therefore it would
be a debate about קנס. Knas. The גמרא's Gemara's saying that's not
true, everybody would agree that they get קנס, Knas, everybody would agree
that the presumption is
One position says yes he does win because he was right to
assume that they were virgins. The other says no, we will take
the position of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that there's a possible counter-claim
she can make and we basically will represent her in that counter-claim
and therefore the husband will not win. Okay, all right, so that
was the חרשת hereshet and the שוטה. shoteh. Again, fascinating that it's
saying that we do assume that they're virgins because again, I would
imagine then as now that these are often people that other people
will take advantage of and maybe cannot make the same types of
assumptions. All right, thank you by the way for the coffee. Go
ahead.
Just a quick question. So about this, so the חרשת hereshet and
the שוטה, shoteh, so like how do you actually give her the
כתובה? kesuvah?
You mean like who's taking care of her money for her? Okay,
so there's issues. There's like, the court will also assign אפיטרופוס, apotropus,
right, people to take exactly. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
goes on. Okay, so והבוגרת אין לה טענת בתולים. ve-habogeret ein la
tanas besulim. A בוגרת bogeres does not have a claim of virgins,
right? She doesn't have a claim of virginity, כתובה kesuvah 200, but
she doesn't have a טענת בתולים. tanas besulim. What does this mean?
We assume that a בוגרת bogeres by definition doesn't necessarily have a
intact hymen, it says מוכת עץ. mukas eitz. מוכת עץ, mukas eitz,
we understand מוכת עץ mukas eitz is the woman that doesn't actually
have a hymen and anyway there was the whole debate before about
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים Chachamim is she considered בתולה
besulah 200, 100? But anyway, that's a case where physically she doesn't
have a hymen, so there's no טענת בתולים. tanas besulim. But what
about בוגרת, bogeres, right? So the גמרא Gemara says we assume a
בוגרת, bogeres, the hymen is no longer intact? ואמר רב, ve-amar Rav,
so now we're getting way back to first פרק perek discussions, okay,
we're little digressing from the whole issue about קנס. knas. ואמר רב
בוגרת נותנין לה לילה ראשונה. ve-amar Rav bogeres nosnin la layla rishona.
Rav says that a בוגרת bogeres has the first night. What does
this mean? It goes back, you might remember the debate of or
the issue of בית הלל בית שמאי Beis Hillel Beis Shammai about
a woman who is on her wedding night, this is a נדה
niddah discussion and she bleeds. So nowadays we assume that anytime a
woman is a virgin, the hymen'll bleeding, we treat it as if
it's דם נדה dam niddah and we automatically make her נדה. niddah.
But in the time of the משנה Mishnah and in different stages
within the גמרא, Gemara, it was an issue that developed over time
in the גמרא, Gemara, basically it was the opposite. We assumed that
any bleeding can be attributed to hymenal bleeding and therefore is not
נדה. niddah. And then the question becomes how much bleeding after the
wedding night do we still assume is hymenal bleeding and therefore not
a problem? So if she was a younger woman, if she was
a נערה, na'arah, we give her more time. If she was a
woman that hasn't even regularly had her period yet, we give her
even more time. But let's say she's a woman who's regularly been
having her period and she's a בוגרת, bogeres, how much bleeding can
we attribute to the hymenal bleeding and make her not a נדה?
niddah? Only the first night, לילה ראשונה. layla rishona. Okay, fine, but
what it does show you is that the first night there will
be hymenal bleeding. So therefore what do we mean when we say
a בוגרת bogeres doesn't have טענת בתולים, tanas besulim, which means that
he should have expected that there was no hymen that she wasn't
a בתולה? besulah? We assume that there is hymen and there will
be hymenal bleeding. So of course so that shows that we do
expect that not only is she a בתולה besulah from the perspective
of never having had sex, but she's also a בתולה besulah from
the perspective of the hymen is still intact. Okay, we do assume
that by a בוגרת. bogeres. So therefore if that wasn't the case,
why is his claim not a legitimate claim? There was no blood
the wedding night, that's what he'll say.
What forces רש״י Rashi to say בועל כמה בעילות? bo'el kama be'ilos?
Because it's לילה ראשונה, layla rishona, it's the whole first night. It's
not just the first act of sex. So he's explaining the halachic
implications,
all bleeding the first night even if it's after many act even
through many acts of sex will all be attributed to hymenal bleeding.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אי דקא טעין, ei de-ka ta'in,
so the top of ל״ו עמוד ב׳, lamed vav amud beis, אי
דקא טעין טענת דמים, ei de-ka ta'in tanas damim, הכא נמי. hacha
nami.
So if he says there was no blood, then you know what,
then he would be believed. Then I mean then it would be
a good claim because we assume a בוגרת bogeres the hymen is
still intact and there will be blood and therefore if he says
there wasn't blood then we say okay he assumed she was a
virgin, obviously had she been a virgin then there would have been
bleeding. There wasn't bleeding, so that's good evidence because even a בוגרת
bogeres we assume there's going to be blood. So he has a
claim she wasn't a virgin. But הכא נמי, hacha nami, הכא במאי
עסקינן, hacha be-mai askinan, what are we talking about? דקא טעין טענת
פתח פתוח. de-ka ta'in tanas pesach pasuach. He didn't make a claim
about the blood. He said I didn't check for the blood, I
didn't notice if there was bleeding or not, but I can tell
you is it didn't feel like she was a virgin because you
know of the פתח פתוח pesach pasuach claim. It felt like the
door was already open in terms of you know how much like
you know how how tight the experience was or not. So that
if you remember was the earlier discussion. That the גמרא Gemara says
ah that's not a claim, because by a בוגרת bogeres by the
time her body has developed a little bit it might feel to
you the man, assuming anyway there's a whole discussion last time whether
we even believe him in his claim not is he knows what
he's talking about when he says פתח פתוח. pesach pasuach. But even
if we assume that he can experientially know what he's talking about,
we say it would have felt it feels different way now that
she's you know a little more mature. It's not going to feel
the same way. So any claim of פתח פתוח pesach pasuach is
not meaningful, it doesn't prove anything. But the claim of lack of
blood that does say something because even by a בוגרת bogeres we
would have assumed that there would have been blood. So just when
you thought we were out of all of those uncomfortable discussions from
the first פרק, perek, we get an opportunity to revisit it right
now. But moving right along. Okay, I don't know which is better
to be discussing the cases of rape or to be discussing the
cases of פתח פתוח. pesach pasuach. Anyway, סומכוס אומר משום רבי מאיר,
Sumchus
omer
mishum Rabbi Meir, סומא אין לה טענת בתולים. suma ein la ta'anat
betulim. So by a סומא, suma, the guy cannot claim oh she
wasn't a virgin and let's reduce the כתובה, ketubah, because we basically
say to him you should have expected she wasn't. Now why is
a סומא suma different? That's not clear. Let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says again, you could always make the issue about
taking advantage, but the גמרא Gemara didn't seem to feel that that
was an issue by חרשת ושוטה. chereshet v'shota. So מאי טעמא דסומכוס?
mai ta'ama de'Sumchus? What's the reason of סומכוס? Sumchus? אמר רב זירא
מפני שנחבטת על גבי קרקע, Amar Rav Zeira mipnei shenichbetet al gabei
karka, because she'll trip on the ground and maybe she'll have some
type of an injury that will basically make her מוכת עץ, mukat
etz, which will cause the hymen to rupture. And therefore you have
to assume that so if he says oh there was no hymenal
bleeding on the wedding night we say yeah whatever that's not a
claim. She probably happened through some other accident and you should have
anyway expected that. So the גמרא Gemara says כולן נמי חבוטי מיחבטן?
kulan nami chabutei michabtan? So all people trip and have accidents and
not just blind people that have accidents. All people have accidents. And
it's nice that the גמרא Gemara doesn't insist that blind people get
into accidents more than people with sight. I do wonder it's an
interesting question how much in the time of the גמרא Gemara were
blind people able to navigate in terms of echolocation or the type
of the walking stick or whatever. I don't know. Anyway, but the
גמרא Gemara doesn't claim that it doesn't come back and say no
but they have more accidents. That's not the גמרא's Gemara's answer. The
גמרא's Gemara's answer is no.
כולן רואות ומראות לאמן. kulan ro'ot u'mar'ot l'iman. If any
young girl has an accident and then she sees some blood coming
out from between her legs, then she'll go tell her mother what
happened and her mother will say oh so sounds like your hymen
got ruptured.
זו אינה רואה ואינה מראה לאמה. zo eina ro'a v'eina mar'a l'ima.
This one doesn't see what happened and therefore doesn't say anything to
her mother and therefore she thinks that she still is a בתולה
betulah in the sense of the hymen is still intact when it
isn't. So it means that
a guy marries a normal woman since she doesn't say by the
way you should know that
a sighted woman... Oh I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
I'll just erase the tape.
Okay, a sighted
woman. I just meant that there was a legally distinct case. All
right fine, all right all right all right.
חטאתי עויתי פשעתי.
chatati
aviti pashati.
What?
You were literally saying that a blind woman wouldn't have a sense
a perception of that. Right.
Well that's also true.
Yeah I know.
But she could still I understand that.
But she knows she's wet she's in the shower?
Right. Yeah I was wondering about that too. And she could
also you feel something and you smell it and you could also
get a sense of what it is by its thickness. I was
also very much wondering about that. What does it think? It thinks
that the blood just falls on the ground not on her body?
Yeah. So I also did not understand that. So but the argument
is is that a woman with sight who basically gets married, it's
like since she doesn't say anything to the husband he has a
right to assume that she's a virgin and implicitly the hymen is
still intact and if he finds out the wedding night that's not
the case then he that's his טענה, ta'ana, either that's evidence that
she isn't a virgin, however you define virginity in terms of hymen
or having had sex, but he had the right to assume that
she was a virgin on all accounts. Whereas this woman, we basically
say the next morning we say you didn't have a right to
assume that because maybe she, not like we assume it always happens,
but maybe she had some accident and she wouldn't have known to
have told
you that she was a basically a מוכת עץ. mukat etz. So
that's סומכוס's Sumchus's opinion. But yes I agree that it's bizarre that
we assume that she wouldn't be able to know that something was
amiss.
Putting her in a category with the שוטה shota almost.
According to סומכוס Sumchus and רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but it's giving
a different explanation for it. Right.
It wasn't just the concept that oh she wouldn't know what's happening
to her.
Right. In terms of that. Right. So the גמרא Gemara now says
והיוצאת משום שם רע אין לה קנס ולא פיתוי. v'hayotzet mishum shem
ra ein la knas v'lo pitu'i. So that was the end of
the contradictory ברייתות. braitot. Now we go back to the first ברייתא
braita we started with, which says that another woman who doesn't get
קנס knas is a woman who's being divorced because of שם רע.
shem ra. Now שם רע shem ra is the case in the
תורה Torah והוציא עליה שם רע v'hotzi aleha shem ra and normally
when that claim is proven then it proves she committed adultery and
then she's not just getting divorced she's actually getting stoned. Right. She's
actually getting executed. And anyway that's a woman who's been married. So
if the woman's been married what's the case about a נערה בתולה?
na'arah betulah? What's even going on here? So the גמרא Gemara says
היוצאת משום שם רע. hayotzet mishum shem ra. So the גמרא Gemara
says בסקילה היא? b'skila hi?
So she's getting stoned. Okay.
So תוספות Tosafot actually has two interesting explanations about what this challenge
is. If you take a look at תוספות Tosafot היוצאת משום שם
רע בסקילה היא, hayotzet mishum shem ra b'skila hi, תוספות Tosafot says
ופשיטא דלאו בת קנס
היא דהא בעולה ודאי היא, u'pshita d'lav bat
knas hi d'ha be'ula vadai hi,
right,
because she's definitely now have had sex. I mean she committed adultery,
that's why she's getting stoned. Okay, so that's one explanation. ואין לפרש
דשיש לה חיוב סקילה הבא עליה פשיטא דאין לה קנס דקים ליה
בדרבה מיניה. v'ein leforesh d'she'yesh la chiyuv skila haba aleha pshita d'ein
la knas d'kam lei b'drabba minei. You can't just say it means
that if she's married then that would override קנס knas because of
the principle of קים ליה. kam lei. Maybe she's a virgin and
married and the guy who therefore
So because basically there cases where we might not say, you know,
cases of קים ליה Kim lei and that gets back to that
whole conversation. Okay, anyway, so let's go on.
What's the difference between אשת המתנבבת משום שם רע Eishet hamitnabevet mishum
shem ra and סוטה? Sotah?
סוטה Sotah is just a ספק? safek?
Yeah. Yeah. And this is right, yeah, סוטה Sotah is a ספק.
safek. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
of course, you know, so anyway, so it says בת סקילה, bat
sekilah, it could either mean the interesting point is is that in
theory a woman could be if you bracket the point I was
making by the תוספות Tosafot is that if you bracket קים ליה,
Kim lei, right, the fact when the תורה Torah says if a
man rapes a נערה בתולה na'ara betulah etc., right, and he pays,
right, and then it
says ולא תהיה לאישה velo tihyeh le'ishah etc., right, if I said
what if the woman was married? I don't think your response would
be oh then he doesn't pay because of קים ליה Kim lei
or then he doesn't pay because she's not a בתולה. betulah. Presumably,
we assume that right for us, the גמרא Gemara assumes נערה, na'ara,
right, you know, I mean the גמרא Gemara basically assumes, you know,
assumes that that's a question about her age, but I think that
we assume that the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is that
she's דוקא davka not married, that's like implicit in describing the case.
Okay, so it's interesting here is is that, you know, is that
you could have said, oh of course that's not included, she's married.
But תוספות Tosafot says no, no, the fact that she's married is
just because therefore we assume that she's a בעולה be'ulah or therefore
there's a principle of קים ליה Kim lei that would kick in,
but the married state itself would not necessarily exclude her, you know,
in terms of her status automatically from that category. But that's the
גמרא's Gemara question. The גמרא Gemara says, okay, but how could she
get a קנס? knas? She's a בת סקילה, bat sekilah, which means
that she's definitely a בעולה. be'ulah. All right, so the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר רב ששת הכי קאמר. Amar Rav Sheshet hachi ka'amar. Now
this is how you have to read it. מי שיצא לה שם
רע בילדותה אין לה קנס. Mi sheyatza lah shem ra beyalduta ein
lah knas.
We're not talking about the biblical שם רע shem ra that the
husband says she committed adultery and it's been proven etc. It means
יוצאת yotzet because what does the word יוצאת yotzet mean? We assume
יוצאת yotzet means that the husband was divorcing her because of a
שם רע, shem ra, which means that adultery had been substantiated. Says
no, יוצאת משום שם רע yotzet mishum shem ra means like the
the rumor has gone out that she is, well, maybe she's had
others, I don't know, but that גמרא's... Gemara the rumor has gone
out that she is, you know, that she sleeps around. Okay, that
she's promiscuous. And therefore you have to assume that she's a בעולה.
be'ulah. Okay, so that's how we're reading it. A very different take.
Meaning if she went out the other thing, then she's promiscuous like
pre-teen, right, essentially? What? Meaning when was the rumor out?
This whole thing
is about נערות na'arot and בגרות. bagrut.
Okay, so let's take a right, that's true, but let's take a
look what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so so the גמרא Gemara
says, so אין לה קנס ein lah knas ולא פשיטא. velo peshita.
אמר רב פפא שמע מינה, Amar Rav Pappa shma mina, so from
here we can infer that if it's just because of a rumor
and we make certain assumptions, so האי שטרא רעיא, hai shtra ra'aya,
if there's a document that's been that's been suspect, no proof, but
people are saying oh look to me I heard that it was
forged and it's just a rumor, לא מגבינן ביה, la magbinan beih,
we won't use it. So we here the question how much does
does law pay attention to rumors? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
היכי דמי, heichi dami, let's figure out this case. אילימא דנפק קלא
עליה דשטרא דזיופא הוא, Ilema denafik kala aleih deshtra deziyufa hu, what's
the case that you would say we wouldn't use a document? If
there's just like a rumor that it's a forgery. דכוותה, Dechavata, would
you say they're in parallel, הכא דנפק עלה קלא דזנאי, hacha denafik
alah kala dezenai, that if a woman has if there's a rumor
that she's promiscuous, that then we just assume it's true?
זיופא וזנאי, Ziyufa vezenai, maybe. והאמר רבא, Veha'amar Rava, doesn't רבא Rava
say יצא לה שם מזנה בעיר אין חוששין לה,
yatza lah shem mezana
ba'ir ein chosheshin lah, even if there's a rumor that in the
city in the town that this woman is promiscuous, that's nothing you
don't you're not concerned about it, you don't pay any legal attention
to it, any הלכתית halachic attention, it has no weight? So clearly
we're not just talking about סתם stam people are gossiping. That wouldn't
have any weight. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא, ela, so here
must be the case where where we assume that there's a real
sub there might be real substance and we have to be הלכתית
halachically concerned about it in terms of this issue of קנס. knas.
דאתו בי תרי ואמרי, De'atu bei terei ve'amri, two people say, come,
so number one it's witnesses, there's two people, okay, and they're testifying,
it's not just סתם stam people gossiping, and they're giving firsthand account.
Now what are they giving firsthand account as? If they say that
they saw her to actually start sleep with another guy, then that's
just not that's not just a rumor, that's actually witnessing that she's
a בעולה. be'ulah. So what can we say that would create a
presumption without being fact but still is better than rumor? So here's
what they say. Two people come and they
testify ואמרי לדידי אמר לן... ve'amri ledidi amar lan... I'm sorry, first
we're going to start with the שטר shtar case then we're going
to get to the woman case. So that two men come two
men come and testify that in the case of the שטר shtar
this מלוה, malveh, the guy who's saying that he has a hundred
dollar שטר shtar against this person, came to them and said to
them לדידי אמר לן, ledidi amar lan, זייפו לי, zayfu li, forge
for me a document. Okay, so they said ראובן Reuven now is
taking out a thousand dollar
שטר shtar against שמעון Shimon דאתו בי תרי ואמרי לדידי אמר לן
חזינהו דעביד איסורא. de'atu bei terei ve'amri ledidi amar lan chazinhu de'avid
issura. Oh, okay, so I did I did skip. you know, not
seduced, oh, could be seduced, but anyway, basically asked us to have
sex with her. Okay, so therefore, it's actual hard evidence about an
actual case that occurred. It's not סתם stam a rumor, but the
case isn't that they saw her have sex, but they saw her
act in a very promiscuous way. She
propositioned us.
If it were the other way around, it wouldn't be believed, right?
Correct, right, right.
Okay, anyway, wouldn't say anything about her status. But if she's coming
and propositioning strange men who she's not married to, whatever, that creates
a presumption that presumably she slept with somebody if she didn't sleep
with them. Okay, and therefore she has to be, there's a concern
that she's a בעולה beulah in terms of the קנס. knas. So
the Gemara says, דכוותה הכא, dechvasah hacha, so on parallel by the
שטר, shtar, דאתו בי תרי ואמרו, de'atu bei terei ve'amri, two people
come and say, לדידי אמר להו זייפו לי. lididi amar lehu zaifu
li. I see people say, so Shimon has a thousand dollar שטר
shtar against, Reuven has a thousand dollar שטר shtar against Shimon, these
witnesses come and say, we don't know about that שטר, shtar, but
what I can tell you is, Reuven came to us a week
ago and said forge for me a שטר shtar against Shimon. Okay,
so we didn't, and I don't know about this שטר shtar per
se, but I'm going to tell you that a week ago he
was asking us to forge a שטר shtar just like that. Okay,
and therefore we won't use the שטר shtar because that creates a
real concrete suspicion of the validity of this שטר. shtar. So the
Gemara says, בשלמא, bishlama, one minute, the Gemara says, I'm not sure
if you can compare the cases. בשלמא התם שכיחי פרוצים. bishlama hasam
shechichi prutzim. I get the case by the woman propositioning the men.
That even though they said no, we have to be concerned that
she slept with somebody, because you'll always find somebody who will say
yes. Okay, so there are people who are not, who are not,
you know, restrained, who are promiscuous, men who are promiscuous as well.
And if a woman's going around propositioning, we have to assume that
somebody's going to say yes. Okay, so therefore that's why we have
that presumption based on their testimony. אלא הכא, ela hacha, if he
was הוחזק, huchzak, כשרה מוקמינן? kashera mokeminan?
Just because we know that Reuven is looking to forge a שטר,
shtar, we have to assume that most, that, you know, anybody he'll
ask will do the right thing and won't forge? So meaning it's
interesting, we can assume that people that are propositioned, will, you know,
men that are propositioned, eventually you're going to find somebody that's going
to say yes, but people that are propositioned to forge a document,
presumably even offered money to do so, they're going to have a
חזקת כשרות chezkas kashrus and we can hope assume that nobody ever
said yes. Okay, it's interesting. I'd say that that's, you know, an
interesting assessment of human nature. Okay, so the Gemara says, no. הכא
נמי, hacha nami, here too, it's not true, eventually you're going to
find someone to say yes. כיון דקמהדר אזיופא אימור זייופי זייף. kevan
d'kamahader aziyupha eimar zeiyuphi zeiyeiph. Oh, no, excuse me, it doesn't say
you'll find someone to say yes. כיון דמהדר אזיופא, kevan d'mahader aziyupha,
since you're looking around to find somebody to forge
it, אימור זייופי זייף, eimar zeiyuphi zeiyeiph, and even if you can't
find other people to forge it, you'll forge it yourself. Okay, so
even in the end, the Gemara is saying that we would more,
we're going to readily, we'll more readily assume that a man will
say yes to this woman propositioning them than we'll assume that anybody
ever said yes to forge a document. Okay, so it's quite, presumably
even though they're being offered money. So that's fascinating. But again, there's
no difference.
I don't know about that.
Okay, anyway, alright, but that's the Gemara's difference that if there's some
concrete evidence of certain behavior, just rumor isn't enough, but concrete evidence
of certain behavior, that will at least create a presumption that she's
not a בתולה besulah for the purpose of the issue of קנס.
knas.
Now the Gemara takes this פיתוי pittuy as an additional type of
קנס knas that's also a money.
So no. פיתוי, pittuy, yeah, תוספות Tosafos asks why it says קנס
knas and פיתוי pittuy since by פיתוי pittuy also there's, it's the
same קנס. knas. Right. It's just to explicitly include the case of
מפותה. mefuteh. And תוספות Tosafos has another explanation, but let's just assume
that's true.
So the ברייתא Beraita didn't mention פיתוי. pittuy.
Yeah, presumably, yeah, presumably. We're going to assume it's all the same.
Okay, next משנה. Mishnah.
And this משנה Mishnah parallels the first one and, as we'll see,
sort of says things that we've been assuming for the last week.
ואלו שאין להן קנס, v'eilu she'ein lahen knas, the following don't have
a קנס. knas. And first we're going to list people who are
assumed to be a בעולה, beulah, not a בתולה. besulah. הבא על
הגיורת ועל השבויה ועל השפחה, haba al hagiyoras v'al hashvuya v'al hashifcha,
a convert, a woman who's converted or a woman that was taken
captive or a woman who is a slave, a non-Jewish slave, שנפדו
ושנתגיירו ושנשתחררו, shenifdu v'shenitgeiyeru v'shenishtachreru, and now they've been either redeemed or
converted or freed, יתירה מבנות שלש שנים ויום אחד, yeseirah mibnos shalosh
shanim v'yom echad,
if their transition happened when they were more than three years old,
then we have to assume that in their state of non-Jew, slave,
or captivity, they actually had either consensual or non-consensual sex. And since
it happened after the age of three, that made them a non-בתולה,
besulah, both in terms of the act of sex, it was considered
an act of sex, and that the hymen would have ruptured and
not come back. So therefore these women because we assume in their
state they are having consensual or non-consensual sex, and it was, their
state was when they were older than three, they are considered to
be a בעולה. beulah. רבי יהודה אומר שבויה שנפדית הרי בקדושתה. Rabbi
Yehuda omer shvuya sheniftes harei bekedushata. Now he has an interesting position
because we've spent a whole סוגיא sugya about a woman who is
a שבויה shvuya and is she מותרת muteres to her husband a
כהן kohen and do we assume that a woman taken captive has
been raped. And here רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda basically says, no, a
שבויה shvuya who has been redeemed, we assume she retains her sanctity,
meaning we assume that she's not been raped, אף על פי שגדולה
af al pi shegdola even if she's an adult. So therefore a
שבויה shvuya even as an adult gets a קנס knas and of
course then the obvious question is, so should we be, would she
be allowed to go back to her husband the כהן? kohen? Why
didn't we say this earlier? Tell me she can go back to
her husband the כהן. kohen. So we'll see about that in the
גמרא. Gemara. So that's the cases about assuming somebody is a בעולה.
beula. Now we get back to the case about personal status and
the cases where the it's not just a woman that there's no
קידושין kiddushin binding like sister where the first משנה Mishna said that
even with no קידושין kiddushin possible at all, there's still going to
be a קנס. knas. Here it's going to be a woman who
actually is a case of incest that is חייבי מיתה, chayvei misa,
that is punishable by the death penalty. הבא על בתו, haba al
bito, if a man has sex with his daughter, על בת בתו,
al bas bito, על בת בנו al bas bno or his granddaughter,
על בת אשתו, al bas ishto, his stepdaughter, his wife's daughter, על
בת בנה al bas bna or her, or his wife's granddaughter, על
בת בתה al bas bita or her whatever granddaughter either way, okay,
all those are cases about חייבי מיתות. chayvei misos. אין להם קנס,
ein lahem knas, no קנס. knas. Now why? Even if there's קנס
knas even if there's no possibility of קידושין, kiddushin, why is this
different than the case of sister? And now we have what we've
been assuming for the last week, מפני שמתחייב בנפשו, mipnei shemischayev bnafsho,
because it is a sin deserving of death. שמיתתם בידי בית דין,
shemisasam biyedei beis din, that and it would actually be with the
right evidence and the right intent it would be put to death
in court. וכל המתחייב בנפשו, vechol hamischayev bnafsho, and anybody who is
doing something that is basically you know liable for their very life,
is doing a capital offense, אין משלם ממון, ein meshalem mamon, doesn't
pay money, שנאמר, shene'emar, ואם לא יהיה אסון ענוש יענש. ve'im lo
yihye ason anosh ye'anesh. If there is no tragedy, there's no death,
then you pay the fine. If the woman in the case of
the miscarriage or whatever dies and it's an act of murder, then
even if it's not going to be, even if the person won't
be executed, therefore there will not be any monetary payment. So now
you understand why for the last week not only have we been
assuming that in the case of חייב מיתה chayav misa it overrides,
but why we were focusing on the issue about אסון ason and
this פסוק pasuk about אסון ason right as the basis for saying
that it overrides because
that is the פסוק pasuk used in this משנה. Mishna. Okay. So
the גמרא's Gemara thankfully not going to revisit really the case of,
I mean it's going to revisit a little bit, but not today
the case of קים ליה, kam lei, we're going to now just
continue to focus for a while on the issue about the קנס.
knas. Yes.
So if there is an אסון, ason, according to פשט pshat of
that פסוק, pasuk, if there is אסון, ason, it's still, it was,
that death was בשוגג, beshogeg, right?
So that gets to the question about חזקיה תנא דבי חזקיה, Chizkiya
tana devei Chizkiya, חייבי מיתות שוגגין. chayvei misos shogegin. Okay. And then
the question is אסון ason or דין אסון din ason and so
on.
Could it be possible that the דרשה drasha here in, is a
דרשה drasha here is אסון ason meaning
the person's death, that is the murderer's death, not her death?
Well no, that's what the גמרא Gemara refers to as דין אסון,
din ason, but that does not sound like פשט pshat in the
משנה Mishna because then the משנה Mishna would not say that you
don't pay קנס, knas, it would only have said you don't pay
קנס knas if actually there was עדים והתראה eidim vehasra'ah and you're
being put to death. So the משנה Mishna seems to categorically say
there's no קנס, knas, which means any type of a capital offense
even if it's not with the conditions that would actually execute the
person, that would still override. Okay and that's what the גמרא Gemara
discusses about you know תנא דבי חזקיה tana devei Chizkiya and
the
difference between אסון ason and דין אסון din ason etcetera. Okay. אמר
רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יהודה ורבי דוסא אמרו דבר אחד.
Rabbi Yehuda veRabbi Dosa amru davar echad. רבי יהודה ורבי דוסא Rabbi
Yehuda veRabbi Dosa said the same thing. רבי יהודה הא דאמרן, Rabbi
Yehuda ha de'amran, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we just said that he
says that we assume a שבויה shvuya still a, is still a
virgin or has not been raped. רבי דוסא דתניא, Rabbi Dosa detanya,
רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa we taught, שבויה אוכלת בתרומה דברי רבי דוסא.
shvuya ocheles bitruma divrei Rabbi Dosa. If a woman was captive and
then she comes back and she's let's say married to a כהן,
kohen, she can continue to eat, or let's say not a case
of married to a כהן, kohen, let's say she's a בת כהן,
bas kohen, she can continue to eat תרומה, truma, okay where if
she had had sex with a non-Jew even if it was nonconsensual,
that would have invalidated her from eating תרומה. truma. So it's the
same assumption, the assumption is that we assume she's not raped, דברי
רבי דוסא. divrei Rabbi Dosa. אמר רבי דוסא amar Rabbi Dosa and
now he's going to explain his position: וכי מה עשה
לה ערבי הלז? vechi ma asa la Aravi halaz? What did this
captor do to her? Interesting he refers to him as an ערבי,
Aravi, an Arab. Okay so תוספות Tosafos has some discussion there about
like maybe certain assumptions they made about the character of whatever, certain
national characteristics or whatever, racial characteristics but we're going to bracket that.
Okay what did this captor do to her? וכי מפני שמישמש לה
בין דדיה פסלה מן הכהונה? vechi mipnei shemishmesh la bein dadeha pasla
min hakehuna? Is it just because he fondled her breasts that he
should invalidate her from כהונה? kehuna? So he basically says yeah, captors
do not rape their, their captives. Okay I don't know why he
assumes that but that was his assumption, maybe they might do some
type of
But they're
not actually going to rape them and therefore we do not have
to assume that she was raped and it does not change her
status. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, דילמא
לא היא, dilma lo hi, although it's true that both רבי דוסא
Rabbi Dosa and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda are assuming they're not raped,
they applied them in different areas of הלכה. halacha. And maybe they
did not mean across the board. Maybe each one only applied it
to his area of הלכה halacha and would assume you can't make
that assumption in other areas. Why? עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהודה
הכא, Ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehuda hacha, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
only says that we assume that she hasn't been raped, that she's
still a virgin, אלא שלא יהא חוטא נשכר. ella shelo yehei chote
nishkar.
So because basically it's an interesting point about policy consideration. The rapist
pays his fifty שקל. shekel. So if he's not going to pay
for whatever technicality, then it's going to be a sinner, somebody who
actually, you know, raped or even a case of seduced this woman,
is going to do it without there being the same type of
consequences, right? So he's going to be he's going to benefit in
the sense that he'll have done his this terrible act and he'll
be free from at least some of the consequences. So therefore we
have a policy reason to want to insist that the קנס knas
should apply in as many cases as possible. So given that we
have a doubt, should we assume a woman who was taken captive
was raped or not? Is she a virgin or not? So maybe
you'll say, you know what? In the case of קנס knas I'm
going to assume she's a virgin because I have a policy reason
why I want to ensure that קנס knas is applied to as
many possible cases as possible in a case of rape and seduction.
That we have as few exceptions as possible to the הלכות halachot
of קנס. knas. Okay? So that's why he'll be willing to assume
in our case to assume that she's still a virgin.
That's what it means by חוטא נשכר chote nishkar here. In other
words, so that in other cases, no, that a
case of a rape you don't get the guy doesn't get away
without paying. If he were to get away without paying, the sinner,
the rapist, would be נשכר, nishkar, would benefit that he'd get away
without paying. So therefore maybe he's not a hundred percent sure she's
still a virgin, but he's willing to assume it for הלכות halachot
of קנס. knas. Because he doesn't want people to escape the punishment
of קנס. knas. Okay.
How does that prevent people from escaping the punishment of קנס? knas?
You're closing loopholes.
If you assume she's a
virgin, then you have to pay the fifty שקל. shekel. Here's a
woman that was taken captive and a year later somebody raped her.
So if we say that a woman who was taken captive isn't
a קנס, knas, א, alef, you could just say that people will
be more ready to take abuse of her, right? Okay, fine. But
it's
after she's free, in other words, somebody will, right, will have to
treat her as if she's exactly.
Exactly. Okay. So, right, it's at first she was taken captive and
then sometime after she was free she was raped. Right. So therefore
because of that policy reason he's going to assume she's still a
virgin. אבל התם, Aval hatam, when it comes to תרומה, Terumah, כרבנן
סבירא ליה, k'rabbanan seira leh, he'll say, look, I would be more
מחמיר machmir when it comes to תרומה Terumah and say don't eat
תרומה, Terumah, maybe she was, don't let her eat תרומה, Terumah, maybe
she actually was raped. But, you know, but for other הלכות halachos
I'm going to treat her, but for the הלכה halacha of קנס
knas I'm going to treat her like a virgin. Okay. אינמי, Inami,
or you say the reverse. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי דוסא התם,
Ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Dosa hatam, when does רבי דוסא Rabbi
Dosa say that she can we can assume she's still a virgin
and she can eat תרומה, Terumah, or not virgin, whatever, she hasn't
been raped and she can eat תרומה, Terumah, אלא
בתרומה דרבנן, ella be'Terumah de'rabbanan, that's תרומה Terumah which is nowadays תרומה
Terumah is rabbinic. אבל קנס דאורייתא, Aval knas de'oraisa, by paying of
monetary fine which is a biblical issue and it's taking money from
somebody, כרבנן סבירא ליה, k'rabbanan seira leh, maybe he'll say we're going
to have to assume she isn't a virgin. I won't make somebody
pay money unless I can, you know, once there's a serious question.
But for תרומה Terumah I'll be willing to be lenient. So each
area of הלכה halacha has a reason to be maybe more lenient
or more strict. So when they're saying we're going to assume she
hasn't been raped, maybe they're not going to assume it across the
board. Maybe they're only going to assume it in one area of
הלכה halacha and not in another area. Yeah.
So, I mean, unless I'm misinterpreting this, it sounds like there was
the concept of קנס knas even at least in terms of the
time of the משנה, Mishnah, possibly in times of the גמרא, Gemara,
right, that they were enforcing this thing.
Oh, you mean because we're using policy issues of חוטא נשכר? chote
nishkar?
So, I mean, when did this stop?
Well, it's true, I mean, the גמרא Gemara does say that שליחותייהו
קא עבדינן shelichusayhu ka'avdinan and we still דן דיני קנסות. dan dinei
knasos. But even though the גמרא Gemara says things like, like חוטא
נשכר, chote nishkar, it could still be meant more in theory than
in practice. It doesn't actually mean that we're actually practicing these cases.
But anyway. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, I
don't know exactly when, I mean, קנס knas has whole issues about
חוטא נשכר chote nishkar and is שכיח shechich or לא שכיח. lo
shechich. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אמר ליה אביי.
Amar lei Abaye. So אביי Abaye says, וטעמא דרבי יהודה הכא שלא
יהא חוטא נשכר? V'ta'ama de'Rabbi Yehuda hacha shelo yehei chote nishkar? Wait
a minute. You think when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that we
assume she wasn't raped, it doesn't mean an across the board assumption.
It means, you know, we'll make that assumption because of certain policy
reasons, because of חוטא נשכר. chote nishkar. Can you really say that?
והתניא, Veha tanya, רבי יהודה אומר שבויה שנשבית הרי היא בקדושתה, Rabbi
Yehuda omer shviya she'nishbis harei hi b'kedushasa, so same language that we
started with, a שבויה shviya taken captive she's still consumed to be
not having been raped, אפילו בת עשר שנים כתובתה מאתים. Afilu bas
eser shanim kesuvaseh masayim.
Even if she's not, you know, even if she's a whole ripe
age of ten. I don't know what the point of that was.
Anyway, she still gets her whole two hundred כתובה. kesuva. Okay? So
now we're not just saying it about somebody doing this horrific act
of rape; we're saying even for כתובה kesuva הלכות, halachos, we assume
she's a virgin.
What? Oh, a שבויה.
shviya. בת עשר שנים? bas eser shanim?
I don't think so.
I don't know,
that's the way I understood it. I don't know, I don't know,
I don't think so. Okay, anyway, I don't know, but it wouldn't
make sense about the אפילו. afillu. Why? How does your English translate
it?
10 years old. Yeah, בת, bas, although that's I hear your point.
Anyway, okay. So והתם מאי משום דקנסא איכא. vehasam mai mishum deknasa
ika. So if he really doesn't, if he really thinks she might
have been raped and it's only a policy issue because of a
case of because of a case of קנס—oh knas I see why
I was being confusing because I'm talking about being raped as a
שבויה shuyah and then being raped as the קנס. knas. Okay, anyway,
if he actually thinks that she might have been raped as the
שבויה shuyah but there's a policy reason that he wants to insist
the קנס knas is still going to be paid in a later
case of אונס ones ומפתה, umepateh. so then why would he make
the assumption that she's a virgin for כתובה kesubah reasons?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, there's also policy issues going on
there. הכא התם נמי דלמא מאינסי ולא נסבי לה. hacha hasam nami
dilma minsi velo nasvi lah. If you say a woman after being
captive, anybody who marries this woman now after she was taken captive
only pays a hundred for the כתובה, kesubah, not 200, so that'll
people won't be as interested in marrying her because you're basically telling
people you have to assume she was raped. So it's actually a
fascinating גמרא Gemara where the גמרא Gemara is actually saying we don't
exactly know, we make certain assumptions based on policy considerations. So when
it comes to how people are going to treat her, afterwards a
woman's captive all the more we'll want somebody to marry her, right?
Because actually דוקא davka people will treat her as like spoiled goods
or something like that. So there's a real policy reason to insist
no, she's assumed to be a virgin, 200 כתובה, kesubah, and if
somebody rapes her now, has to pay the קנס, knas, assumed to
be a virgin, we want to protect her, protect society, we want
to keep that in place. Okay, but when it comes to the
question should she eat תרומה? terumah? תרומה terumah is a different question.
It's not an issue about how society will perceive her status. Alright,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara says, it could very well be
policy reasons. וסבר רב יהודה דכתובה קיימא? vesavar Rav Yehuda dechesuvah kayama?
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to go on okay and
say is this really true that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda holds that
she's still considered to be a virgin?
But he wouldn't want to marry a כהן kohen would he, רב
יהודה?
Rav Yehuda? Possibly not, and that's what the גמרא Gemara is going
to discuss exactly now. והתניא הפודה את השבויה. vehatanya hapodeh es hashuyah.
If somebody redeems a woman captive and this is assumed to be
a כהן kohen here because a כהן kohen wouldn't be able to
marry her if she had sex with a non-Jew whether consensual or
not, ישאנה, yisena, he can marry her. Okay, which means he can
assume
that she hasn't had sex with this non-Jew. מעיד בה? mai bah?
If he testifies about her that she has not had sex, לא
ישאנה, lo yisena, he can't marry her. Now that's a little bizarre.
Why the more that he knows he can't marry her? So the
גמרא Gemara will get to that. רבי יהודה אומר בין כך ובין
כך לא ישאנה. Rabbi Yehuda omer bein kach uvein kach lo yisena.
And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says in either case he can't marry
her, which is the question, because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the
one that normally assumes she hasn't had sex. Why here does he
say either way he can't marry her? But first the גמרא Gemara
has to explain the first part of the ברייתא. braisa. הגופא קשיא.
hagufa kashya. The beginning is intrinsically contradictory. אמרת הפודה את השבויה ישאנה.
amarta hapodeh es hashuyah yisena. First you said the guy who redeems
her can marry her, presumably even without any special knowledge. והדר תנא
מעיד בה לא ישאנה. vehadar tana mai bah lo yisena. When he
testifies that she hasn't had sex he can't marry her. משום דמעיד
בה לא ישאנה? mishum demai bah lo yisena? Because he testifies and
he knows that she hasn't had sex that's why he can't marry
her? So the גמרא Gemara says no. הא לא קשיא הכי קאמר.
ha lo kashya hachi ka'amar. That's not difficult, this is what it
means. הפודה את השבויה ומעיד בה. hapodeh es hashuyah ume'id bah. If
you redeem a woman and testify about her in normal cases you
can't assume she hasn't had sex, but
if you are not only testifying about her but you're testifying about
her and you say you have definite knowledge she hasn't had sex
and you're the one redeeming her and you're paying money to free
her, then ישאנה yisena you can marry her. מעיד בה כדי. mai
bah kidei. If a guy just testifies about her status but has
not paid the money to redeem her, לא ישאנה, lo yisena, he
can't marry her. Now the reason of the difference is we basically
say that if he didn't pay money to redeem her and he's
just saying that she didn't have sex because he wants to marry
her, maybe he doesn't really know, maybe he's lying. But if he's
actually going to pay good money to redeem her, then he wouldn't
be paying the good money unless actually he was telling the truth,
which is pretty funny. Here you are you're ready to commit your
life with this woman, okay, but maybe you're lying because you're so
attracted to her you're going to lie and say that she actually
didn't have sex. Okay, but if you actually have to first pay
money
where your mouth
is, anyway, that's the assumption. But the way the גמרא Gemara is
reading this ברייתא braisa is and again we're talking about a כהן
kohen for whom this would be a problem, that the assumption would
be that she has had sex unless you can testify that she
has not. מכל מקום קשיא לרבי יהודה. mikol makom kashya le-Rabbi Yehuda.
But now we've got a problem because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
in either situation he can't marry her, which is the exact opposite
of what רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda normal assumption is. His normal assumption
is that she hasn't had sex. Again this is assuming as תוספות
Tosafos points out that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not saying a
policy position. The רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is saying a princ- like
a categorical statement that we assume that she hasn't had sex. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב פפא אימא רבי יהודה אומר בין
כך ובין כך ישאנה. Amar Rav Pappa eima Rebbi Yehuda omer bein
kach u'vein kach yissana. Okay, switch the gears. Have רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda say either way he can marry her, because we assume that
she hasn't- hasn't- hasn't had sex. רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע אומר
לעולם כדקתני. Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua omer l'olam k'diktani. No, it's
like it said, either way he can't, but רבי יהודה לדבריהם דרבנן
קאמר. Rebbi Yehuda l'divrehem d'Rabbanan ka-amar. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is saying
back to the rabbis, you know, according to the way that you're
approaching it, from your perspective. לדידי, L'didi, as far as I'm concerned,
בין כך ובין כך ישאנה, bein kach u'vein kach yissana, either way
he could marry her, because we assume that a woman taken captive
has not been raped. And again, as תוספות Tosfos points out, this
is bracketing saying that it's based on policy, it's based on no,
it's just a general assumption that a woman taken captive we assume
is not raped for all purposes, not just for כתובה, Kesuvah, not
just for קנס, Knas, even for a כהן Kohen marrying her. That's
my position. אלא לדידכו, Ella l'didchu, but you, who generally assume that
she has been raped, בין כך ובין כך לא ישאנה, bein kach
u'vein kach lo yissa'enna, either way he shouldn't marry her, because מיבעי
ליה, mi-ba'ei lei, that's what you should be saying, because why either
way, we should be assuming that even if he's testifying, maybe he's
lying and maybe his יצר הרע yetzer hara got the better of
him. ורבנן, V'Rabbanan, and the rabbis would say back: הפודה את השבויה
ומעיד בה ישאנה. Ha-podeh es hashvuya u'me'id bah yissa'enna. If he not
only is testifying about her that she hasn't been raped, but even
redeeming her and paying money, then we can trust him. לא שדי
איניש זוזי בכדי. Lo shadei inish zuzei b'fichdi.
People don't throw their money away for no- for no reason. Okay,
מעיד בה כדי לא ישאנה, Me'id bah k'dei lo yissa'enna, if he
just testifies without actually redeeming her, then he can't marry her. שמא
עיניו נתן בה, Shema einav nasan bah, maybe he just has his
יצר הרע yetzer hara got the better of him and he wants
to marry her and he's lying about it. Again, it's pretty funny,
he'd be willing to marry her, you know, and stay married to
her for his life—I mean, he could always divorce her I guess—but
that he'd be willing to lie about, but if it actually also
involves paying out money, then he wouldn't be making it up. All
right, anyway. But what we have is that now we are dealing
with רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda position that we assume that she has
not been raped, applied not only in policy areas like קנס knas
and כתובה, kesuvah, but even in great cases like the question about
her allowance to marry a כהן. kohen. Let's just get to the
beginning
of, you know, let's end here because this is like we're going
to continue with this and we're not going to have a chance
to get to the rest of the next day. Yes.
No, מעיד בה me'id bah is not expecting her, מעיד בה me'id
bah is testifying that he...